Guide to the Winston Weisman Collection of Architectural Photographs [1950]-1973 depicting structures ca. 1850 - 1970 PR 73
© 2011 New-York Historical Society
Winston Weisman Collection of Architectural Photographs
ca. 1950-1973
PR 73
© 2011 New-York Historical Society
40.91 Linear feet (98 boxes)
Winston Weisman was an architectural historian and professor. This collection contains his extensive research material (including photographs, negatives, articles, and lectures) on cast-iron buildings in the Soho neighborhood of New York, as well as other buildings throughout the United States and the world.
Provenance
Gift from Winston Weisman in 1975 -- 1986.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to twenty exposures of stable, unbound material per day. (Researchers may not accrue unused copy amounts from previous days.) See guidelines in Reading room for details.
Biographical Note
Architectural historian and professor Dr. Winston R. Weisman, born February 3, 1909 in New York City, compiled extensive pictorial documentation to support several areas of his research: cast-iron architecture, origins of the skyscraper, and commercial architecture in New York City, including the Soho district, Rockefeller Center, and buildings by architect George B. Post. His interest in these particular areas of research date from his 1939 dissertation on Rockefeller Center. He did most of his subsequent research as professor and head of the Department of Art History at the Pennsylvania State University, where he specialized in the history of commercial architecture. He dedicated 22 years to teaching at Penn State between from 1958 -- 1971.
Weisman was educated at Ohio State University where he received his B.A. in art history (cum laude) and journalism in 1932. He completed his M.A. in art history at the Institute of Fine Arts at New York University in 1936. Weisman then received his Ph. D. in art history and studio art from Ohio State University with his dissertation on the genesis of Rockefeller Center.
His research focused on commercial architecture and shaped his academic career, as he often taught classes on the specific subjects he was researching, whether the early history of skyscrapers or cast iron buildings. He did, though, explore other areas of art history, writing two manuals: Medieval Manuscripts Painting A Teaching Manual and An Annotated Portfolio of Photographs Taken from Medieval Manuscripts in the Pierpont Morgan Library, both published in 1949. These two books reflect his developing scholarly interests before he focused exclusively on commercial architecture.
Weisman was director of the College Art Association of American Society of Architectural Historians. He published articles in magazines such as The Architectural Review, Journal of the Society of Architectural Historians, Journal of the American Institute of Architects, and the New York Times Sunday Magazine. He contributed the paper, "The History of the Skyscraper 1907 -- 1917," for the Columbia University Symposium on Modern Architecture in May 1966, then spent the last decades of his life working on and researching the unpublished A History of Commercial Architecture Volume 1: The Elevator Building. This volume was a compendium of all of research and articles on the early skyscraper in various American cities, though predominantly New York. Weisman's essay "A New Vision of Skyscraper History" was one of four specially commissioned for a book, The Rise of American Architecture, published as part of the 100th Anniversary celebration of the Metropolitan Museum of Art in New York.
Two significant projects marked the final years of Weisman's professional career. For the first "Project Soho" in 1970 and 1971, his students recorded a series of thoroughly detailed photos and data sheets documenting the cast iron buildings in Soho. This project continued work that Weisman had begun in the early 1950s. Weisman's historical efforts helped form the basis for the New York City Landmark Commission's final designation report making the Soho Cast-Iron Historical District an official landmark on August 14, 1973.
His second major project was overseeing the dismantling of the Laing Stores in the Soho District of New York City, an historical ironclad structure that was the complete building by James Bogardus standing at the time it was scheduled to be dismantled in the late sixties. In April of 1970, Dr. Weisman was named consultant to the New York City Landmarks Preservation Commission.
He died on October 9, 1997 at the age of eighty-eight.
Historical Note
Cast iron played a preeminent role in the architectural development of New York City and the United States during the 19th century. Cast iron is an alloy with a high carbon content (at least 1.7% and usually 3.0 to 3.7%) that makes it more resistant to corrosion than either wrought iron or steel. In addition to carbon, cast iron contains varying amounts of silicon, sulfur, manganese, and phosphorus. While molten, cast iron is easily poured into molds, making it possible to create nearly unlimited decorative and structural forms. Unlike wrought iron and steel, cast iron is too hard and brittle to be shaped by hammering, rolling, or pressing. However, it is more rigid and more resistant to buckling than other forms of iron.
In the second half of the 19th century, the United States experienced an era of tremendous economic and territorial growth. The use of iron in commercial and public buildings spread rapidly, and hundreds of iron-fronted buildings were erected in cities across the country from 1849 to the early 1900s, especially in New York City. By the turn of the century, steel was becoming available nationally, and was structurally more versatile and cost competitive. Its increased use was one reason why building with cast iron diminished after intensive use for a half century. A large proportion of iron fronts nationwide have been demolished in downtown redevelopment projects, especially since World War II.
James Bogardus (1800 -- 1874) was a major proponent of the use of cast iron, and several of the buildings he designed are represented within this collection. In 1849 Bogardus erected the first structure with self supporting, multistoried exterior walls of iron. The Edgar Laing Stores was a row of small four-story warehouses that appeared as one building, and was constructed in lower Manhattan in only two months. Its rear, side, and interior walls were of brick; the floor framing consisted of timber joists and girders. One of the cast iron walls was load bearing, supporting the wood floor joists. The innovation was its two street facades of self-supporting cast iron, consisting of multiples of only a few pieces: Doric-style engaged columns, panels, sills, and plates, along with some applied ornaments. Each component of the facades had been cast individually in a sand mold by a foundry, machined smooth, tested for fit, and finally trundled on horse-drawn drays to the building site. There they were hoisted into position, then bolted together and fastened to the conventional structure of timber and brick with iron spikes and staps.
Scope and Content Note
The Winston Weisman Collection of Architectural Photographs spans the period from ca. 1950 - 1973 and primarily depicts structures during the period ca. 1850 -- 1950. There are approximately 3,500 prints (8 x 10 in. and smaller) and approximately 3,800 film negatives (4 x 5 in. and smaller). The prints in this collection are accompanied by building reports, lectures, articles, maps and a six-box card file. Photographs and data sheets from the Soho Project are filed alphabetically by street name and have cross-indexing available by architect and building dates. Mounted prints are filed by street address, city, or country, whichever is most appropriate. The card file provides information about many buildings, arranged by date or place.
In addition to photographing extant buildings, Weisman reproduced architectural drawings and book and magazine illustrations depicting structures in the 1800s and early 1900s. The collection's most unique section documents cast-iron structures in the Soho area of lower Manhattan in 1971 through notebooks of photographs and building reports created by Pennsylvania State University students under Weisman's direction. In the largest series, mounted photographs depict commercial buildings in Manhattan (including many in Soho), Chicago, Philadelphia, and a few other United States and foreign cities, chiefly from 1850 to 1950. Weisman captioned many of the photographs with information about architect and building construction dates. There is a large amount of duplication of print copies throughout the various series. The first series of mounted copy prints is the best place to search for any particular image as it is the largest group and, to a large extent but not entirely, has many of the images to be found in the other series. The other important series for specific buildings in Soho or this cast iron area in general is Project Soho and its data sheets. The collection is divided into eleven series: Mounted Copy Prints; Negatives; Card Files; Project Soho; Laing Stores Project; Manhattan Buildings Research; Lectures and Writings; Specific Architects Material; Assorted Unmounted Copy Prints; Oversize Copy Prints; 35 mm. Negatives.
Arrangement
The collection is divided into eleven series:
Series I. Mounted Copy Prints
Series II. Negatives
Series III. Card Files
Series IV. Project Soho
Series V. Laing Stores Project
Series VI. Manhattan Buildings Research
Series VII. Lectures and Writings
Series VIII. Specific Architects Material
Series IX. Assorted Unmounted Copy Prints
Series X. Oversize Copy Prints
Series XI. 35 mm. Negatives
Laing Stores (New York, N.Y.); Pennsylvania State University; Post, George Browne, 1837-1913--Portraits; Rockefeller Center; Weisman, Winston R.; Architectural reocrds; Architecture, Domestic–New York (State)–New York; Articles; Cast-iron fronts (Architecture)–New York (N.Y.); Chicago (Ill.)--Buildings, structures, etc.; Commercial buildings–New York (State)–New York; Film negatives; Historic Buildings--United States; Lectures; Manhattan (New York, N.Y.); Maps; New York (N.Y.)--Buildings, structures, etc.; Notebooks; Philadelphia (Pa.)--Buildings, structures, etc.; Photographs; Skyscrapers; SoHo (New York, N.Y.); United States----Buildings, structures, etc.
- Series I. Mounted Copy Prints 1850 -- 1970
  Scope and Contents note
  Dr. Weisman's interest in early skyscrapers and commercial architecture is well represented in this collection of photos. This series contains approximately 3,500 black and white photographic copy prints, 8 x 10 inches mounted on boards. They depict commercial buildings throughout New York City and its SoHo district, as well as other cities across America, ranging from Albany, Boston, and Chicago to Philadelphia, and also including several foreign cities. All buildings in Manhattan are named, if known, and only significantly represented buildings in other cities are named.
  The mounted prints consist of copy prints of buildings that were used by Winston Weisman in his lectures and research. Many of the prints in this series are taken from books, such as King's Handbook of New York City and Baxter's View: Panorama and Business Directory of Philadelphia: 1856 by D.W.C. Baxter, or from architecture magazines from the period 1850s to the early 20th century. These prints contain material relating to an extensive pictorial documentation to support several areas of Weisman's research, such as that commissioned by Pennsylvania State University -- National Science Foundation "Project Soho", and The New York City Landmark Preservation Commission in the early 1970's in addition to his earlier work on commercial architecture, particularly early skyscrapers and cast iron buildings.
  Of particular note are those cast iron buildings represented beyond the Soho district. Weisman sought out print copies of buildings by James Bogardus whose cast iron works were the earliest and most influential. The Eccentric Mill Works had a complete metal frame, including prefabricated columns, beams and wall panels. It was completed in 1849 at the corner of Duane and Centre streets and disassembled ten years later to widen Duane Street. The most elaborate Bogardus building was Harper and Brothers on Franklin Square in 1854 (razed in 1920). It was not a complete cast iron building like the Eccentric Mill Works as it used masonry in the façade and load bearing walls. Bogardus showed his imagination in the girders he designed for Harper. The girders he provided were of cast iron shaped like arches, with rods along the bottom of wrought iron, a far more elastic material, to correct the problem of cast iron cracking at the bottom due to their crystalline and brittle structure. Soon the wrought-iron rolling mills were turning out full-sized structural members. Bogardus had anticipated the use of extra-strength steels in parts of modern buildings. His second cast iron front building, after the Laing Stores represented in the fifth series in this collection, was a significant leap in terms of size and complexity. Begun in April 1850 by Bogardus, with architect Robert Hatfield, the five-story Sun newspaper building in Baltimore was both cast iron fronted and cast iron framed. Other significant buildings by Bogardus among the mounted copy prints are the watchtower at Mount Morris Park, the John Mihau Drugstore, the McCullough Shot Tower, Charles Ahrenfeldt & Son Building, and the lighthouse at Santo Domingo.
  There is a mounted copy print of a representation from a magazine of the first electric passenger elevator, which was installed in the Demarest Building on Fifth Avenue in New York City in 1889 by the Otis Company. This print is among the several images of early elevators, an important element studied by Weisman in looking at early skyscrapers, which he often referred to as "elevator buildings".
  This series is subdivided into four subseries: Manhattan, Architects, United States, and International Cities.
  - MANHATTAN, NEW YORK (by street address)
    The first subseries is print copies of buildings in Manhattan arranged alphabetically by the address of named streets (such as Broadway or Canal Street), followed by numerical arrangements for the avenues (e.g. Fifth Avenue), and then for the numbered street (e.g. 14th Street). Before each address (such as Broadway or 13th Street) are the buildings that do not have a specific numbered address or are situated on a corner with no predominate numbered address. These are arranged alphabetically or numerically by cross streets. These latter buildings form a much smaller part of the subseries as most of the Manhattan buildings have a specific street address. The end of this subseries includes the miscellaneous identified buildings with no address at all, arranged alphabetically by the name of the building, followed by the unidentified buildings of Manhattan, as well as Soho specifically. The Manhattan subseries is rounded out with copy prints of New York City bridges, panoramic views of Lower Manhattan, maps of Lower Manhattan and Soho, and representations of early elevators in Manhattan buildings.
    - 13 Astor Place (Box 1, Folder 1)
      General note
      drawing of riot at Astor Place Opera
    - 149 Bank Street (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Building for Thomas Cusack Co.
    - Battery Park Project (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - 56 Beaver and South William Street (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Delmonico's
    - Beekman and Pearl Street (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - 3 -- 9 Beekman Street (corner of Nassau) (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Temple Court
    - 12 Beekman Street (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Morse Building
    - 109 Beekman Street (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Bleecker and Wooster Street (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - 67 Bleecker Street (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Bank for Savings in the City of New York
    - 45 -- 153 Bowery Street (Box 1, Folder 11)
      includes New York Theatre, Winter Garden, Bowery Savings Bank
    - 333 Bowery Street (Box 1, Folder 12)
      Dry Dock Savings Bank
    - Bowling Green (Box 1, Folder 13)
      Government House
    - Broad Street views -- no address (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Broad Street and Exchange Place (Box 1, Folder 15)
      Mills Building, Broad Exchange
    - Broad and William Street (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - 8 Broad Street (Box 1, Folder 17)
      New York Stock Exchange
    - 20 Broad Street (Box 1, Folder 18)
      Commercial Cable Building
    - 24 -- 26 Broad Street (Box 1, Folder 19)
      Blair and Co. Building
    - 30 Broad Street (Box 1, Folder 20)
      Johnston Building
    - 31 -- 33 Broad Street (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - 42 -- 44 Broad Street (Box 1, Folder 22)
      Edison Building
    - Broadway and Astor Place (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Broadway and Beaver Street (Box 1, Folder 24)
      Welles Building, Morris Building
    - Broadway and Duane Street (Box 1, Folder 25)
      Mutual Reserve Fund Life Assoc. Building
    - Broadway and Franklin Street (Box 1, Folder 26)
      Taylor's Restaurant
    - Broadway from Trinity Church to Cedar Street (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Broadway view from Vesey and Barclay Streets (Box 1, Folder 28)
      includes Astor House, St. Paul's Chapel
    - Broadway and Wall Street street (Box 1, Folder 29)
      proposed arcade railway under Broadway, United Bank Building
    - Broadway view from Warren to Reade Street (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Broadway view from White to Walker Street (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Broadway and 4th Street (Box 1, Folder 32)
      Lyons Building
    - Broadway and 12th Street (Box 2, Folder 33)
      Weld Building
    - Broadway and 16th Street (Box 2, Folder 34)
      Tiffany Building (proposed)
    - Broadway and 20th Street (Box 2, Folder 35)
      Warren Building
    - Broadway and 22nd Street (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Broadway and 23rd to 26th Street (Madison Square) and Fifth Avenue (Box 2, Folder 37)
      includes Fifth Avenue Hotel, Albermarle Hotel
    - Broadway and 29th Street (Box 2, Folder 38)
      The Breslin
    - Broadway and 31st to 32nd Street (Box 2, Folder 39)
      includes a building for Daniel A. Loring, Imperial Hotel
    - Broadway and 34th Street (Herald Square) (Box 2, Folder 40)
      R.H. Macy & Co. Department Store
    - Broadway and 39th Street (Box 2, Folder 41)
      Metropolitan Opera House
    - Broadway and 66th to 67th Streets (Box 2, Folder 42)
      Hotel Marie Antoinette
    - 1 Broadway (Box 2, Folder 43)
      Washington Building
    - 2 -- 12 Broadway (Box 2, Folder 44)
      New York Produce Exchange and Bank, Bowling Green Building
    - 25 Broadway (Box 2, Folder 45)
      Cunard Building
    - 26 Broadway (Box 2, Folder 46)
      Standard Oil Building
    - 42 Broadway (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - 50 Broadway (Box 2, Folder 48)
      Tower Building
    - 52 -- 56 Broadway (Box 2, Folder 49)
      Exchange Court
    - 58 -- 62 Broadway (Box 2, Folder 50)
      Consolidated Stock and Petroleum Exchange
    - 66 Broadway (Box 2, Folder 51)
      Manhattan Life Insurance Company
    - 71 Broadway (Box 2, Folder 52)
      includes Empire Building
    - 78 -- 82 Broadway (Box 2, Folder 53)
      Union Trust Building
    - 90 -- 106 Broadway (Box 2, Folder 54)
      includes Continental Insurance Co., American Surety Co.
    - 108 -- 119 Broadway (Box 2, Folder 55)
      includes Trinity Building, Bowen and McNamee, Boreel Building
    - 120 Broadway (Box 3, Folder 56)
      Equitable Life Assurance Co.
    - 128 Broadway (Box 3, Folder 57)
      American Exchange National Bank
    - 140 -- 146 Broadway (Box 3, Folder 58)
      Mutual Life Insurance Co., Singer Building, Washington Life Building
    - 149 -- 167 Broadway (Box 3, Folder 59)
      includes Williamsburgh City Fire Insurance Co., Manhattan Life Insurance Co.
    - 171 Broadway (Box 3, Folder 60)
      Gilsey Building
    - 175 -- 176 Broadway (Box 3, Folder 61)
      Williamsburgh Savings Bank, Title Guarantee & Trust Co.
    - 183 Broadway (Box 3, Folder 62)
      John Milhau Drugstore
    - 191 Broadway (Box 3, Folder 63)
      White, Bramhall & Lockwood Building, Mercantile National Bank Building
    - 195 Broadway (Box 3, Folder 64)
      Western Union Telegraph Building
    - 208 Broadway (Box 3, Folder 65)
      Evening Post Building
    - 214 -- 216 Broadway (Box 3, Folder 66)
      National Park Bank
    - 220 Broadway (Box 3, Folder 67)
      St. Paul Building
    - 229 Broadway (Box 3, Folder 68)
      American Hotel
    - 233 Broadway (Box 3, Folder 69)
      Woolworth Building
    - 237 Broadway (Box 3, Folder 70)
      includes Broadway Bank
    - 240 -- 252 Broadway (Box 3, Folder 71)
      includes D'Brandeth Building, Ball, Black and Co. Building
    - 253 Broadway (Box 4, Folder 72)
      Postal Telegraph Cable Company
    - 256 -- 257 Broadway (Box 4, Folder 73)
      Home Life Insurance Co.
    - 263 -- 271 Broadway (Box 4, Folder 74)
      includes National Shoe and Leather Bank
    - 273 -- 287 Broadway (Box 4, Folder 75)
      includes Broadway Chambers Building, A.T. Stewart's Store, Wanamaker's
    - 290 -- 294 Broadway (Box 4, Folder 76)
      Dun Building
    - 302 Broadway (Box 4, Folder 77)
      Vincent (Astor) Building
    - 303 -- 330 Broadway (Box 4, Folder 78)
      includes Masonic Hall, Teft, Weller & Co.
    - 343 -- 348 Broadway (Box 4, Folder 79)
      includes New York Life Insurance Co., Appleton's Book Store
    - 374 -- 378 Broadway (Box 4, Folder 80)
    - 382 -- 394 Broadway (Box 4, Folder 81)
    - 424 -- 426 Broadway (Box 4, Folder 82)
    - 428 -- 432 Broadway (Box 4, Folder 83)
    - 434 -- 438 Broadway (Box 4, Folder 84)
    - 443 -- 458 Broadway (Box 5, Folder 85-86)
    - 461 -- 468 Broadway (Box 5, Folder 87)
      includes Lord and Taylor, Mills and Gibb Warehouse
    - 473 -- 485 Broadway (Box 5, Folder 88-90)
      includes Roosevelt Building
    - 486 Broadway (Box 5, Folder 91)
    - 488 Broadway (Box 6, Folder 92)
      Haughwout Building
    - 495 -- 497 Broadway (Box 6, Folder 93)
      includes Grover and Baker Sewing Maching Co. Building
    - 502 -- 523 Broadway (Box 6, Folder 94)
      including St. Nicholas Hotel
    - 530 Broadway (Box 6, Folder 95)
    - 540 Broadway (Box 6, Folder 96)
    - 542 -- 544 Broadway (Box 6, Folder 97)
    - 548 Broadway (Box 6, Folder 98)
    - 549 -- 555 Broadway (Box 6, Folder 99)
      includes Rouss Building, Tiffany and Co. Building
    - 560 -- 566 Broadway (Box 6, Folder 100-101)
      includes Singer Building
    - 568 - 578 Broadway (Box 6, Folder 102)
    - 580 Broadway (Box 7, Folder 103)
      Metropolitan Hotel
    - 583 -- 587 Broadway (Box 7, Folder 104)
    - 603 - 710 Broadway (Box 7, Folder 105)
      includes Austin Building, Cable Building, Wheeler and Wilson Building, La Farge House
    - 712 Broadway (Box 7, Folder 106)
    - 715 -- 727 Broadway (Box 7, Folder 107)
    - 741 Broadway (Box 7, Folder 108)
    - 751 Broadway (Box 7, Folder 109)
    - 802 -- 804 Broadway (Box 7, Folder 110)
      Grace Church
    - 841 Broadway (Box 7, Folder 111)
      Roosevelt Building
    - 849 -- 853 Broadway (Box 7, Folder 112)
      Domestic Sewing Machine Co. Building
    - 870 Broadway (Box 7, Folder 113)
      McIntyre Building
    - 881 -- 887 Broadway (Box 7, Folder 114)
      Arnold Constable Building
    - 888 Broadway (Box 7, Folder 115)
      Sloane Store
    - 889 -- 892 Broadway (Box 7, Folder 116)
      includes Gorham Manufacturing Co. Building
    - 901 Broadway (Box 7, Folder 117)
      Lord and Taylor
    - 1160 Broadway (Box 7, Folder 118)
    - 1170 Broadway (Box 7, Folder 119)
    - 1181 Broadway (Box 7, Folder 120)
      Baudouine Building
    - 1200 Broadway (Box 7, Folder 121)
    - 1407 Broadway (Box 7, Folder 122)
    - 1413 Broadway (Box 7, Folder 123)